בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף פ, daf peh,
80. We're about two-thirds done with the מסכתא, masecheta, more or less.
Anyway, we pick up on the bottom of עין ט עמוד ב
ayin tet amud bet and the discussion had was Rabbi Akiva, who
says that a סריס אדם, saris adam, somebody who was born
fertile—is that the right word for a man? I don't know if
he's fertile or infertile. What's a man? Same word? Anyway, okay. Anyway,
a man who was born fertile and then through some type of
an act of a human action or some type of an accident
or something became infertile, that person is able, is in the category
of חליצה chalitzah and יבום, yibum, whether he's the person who died
or whether he's the surviving brother, because he was born again fertile,
that puts him fundamentally in that category, even though right now he
can't have kids. And the גמרא Gemara was bothered with the idea
that according to Rabbi Akiva, that type of a person will be
a פצוע דכא וכרות שפכה, ptzua daka u'chrot shofcha, which is an
איסור לאו, issur lav, and for him therefore he should be out
of the category because Rabbi Akiva treats איסור לאו issur lav like
an איסור כרת issur kares in terms of the child being a
ממזר mamzer and excluded from the category of יבום. yibum. And the
גמרא Gemara gave a couple of possible answers: we're talking about a
גיורת, giyoret, another answer, and the last answer let's just reread is
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, one, two, three, six lines from
the bottom, middle of the line, אלא אמר רב יוסף: Ela amar
Rav Yosef: האי תנא התנא דבי רבי עקיבא היא, Hai tana ha
tana de-bei Rabbi Akiva hi, the תנא tanna of our משנה mishnah
that says that for Rabbi Akiva this person who's a פצוע דכא
ptzua daka is in the category of יבום yibum and חליצה chalitzah
is the one from the school of Rabbi Akiva, דאמר מחייבי לאוין
דשאר הוי ממזר מחייבי לאוין גרידי לא הוי ממזר. de-amar mi-chayvei lavin
de-she'er havei mamzer, mi-chayvei lavin geridei lo havei mamzer. So there's a
debate when Rabbi Akiva says an איסור לאו issur lav makes a
ממזר, mamzer, does he mean all איסור לאו, issur lav, or only
an איסור לאו issur lav that's similar to עריות? arayot? That is
שאר, she'er, that is about a type of a, you know, a
relationship, a blood relationship. So what is an איסור לאו issur lav
that's of a blood relationship? We can think of obvious איסור לאוs
issur lav that are not about blood relationships: פצוע דכא, ptzua daka,
כהן kohen
with a, with a, what do you call it, with a
גרושה. gerushah. But what's an איסור issur that's about a שאר, she'er,
an איסור לאו? issur lav? So רש"י Rashi on the earlier דף,
daf, thank you, quotes two, two scenarios. One is a,
if we פסקינן paskin that a woman that a man's father has
had sex with is also forbidden, לא יגלה כנף אביו, lo yigaleh
knaf aviv, so that would be one because of the relationship to
one's father. And the other, and the other idea רש"י Rashi quotes
is if we פסקינן paskin that a man that a woman that
a man did חליצה chalitzah with, right, כיון שלא בנה שוב לא
יבנה. keivan she-lo banah shuv lo yivneh. Those are people that a
man has had a type of some type of a relationship with,
again I'm looking for another word, שאר, she'er, like some type of
a blood connection, and
and is only an איסור—what? issur Kinship. Thank you, that's a good
one. And, and is only an איסור לאו. issur lav. So those
are the ones that Rabbi Akiva would say the child is a
ממזר, mamzer, but some that are a simple איסור לאו issur lav
like a כהן kohen with a גרושה gerushah or our case a
פצוע דכא ptzua daka would not be a ממזר mamzer and would
not be excluded from the category. So that's a nice easy straightforward
answer that Rabbi Akiva is actually narrower. Now the גמרא Gemara turns
its attention away from Rabbi Akiva to the simple and obvious question
which is: how can you say there's a מצוה mitzvah יבום yibum
here or a מצוה mitzvah חליצה chalitzah and the person is in
this category if there are no kids that are possible? Because whatever
the person is בגברא begavro in his status in the category, practically
now he can't have kids. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so the גמרא Gemara now four lines from the bottom: איקרי כאן
להקים לאחיו שם והא לאו בר הכי הוא. Ikri kan le-hakim l'achiv
shem v'ha lav bar hachi hu.
So the גמרא Gemara says: okay, who cares, this type of סריס,
saris, that type of סריס, saris, he can't have kids, you know,
and how can he be in the category of to establish a
name for his brother? It's not possible right now to have kids.
Why can we say there's a מצוה mitzvah of חליצה chalitzah or
יבום? yibum? So אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אם כן, Im ken, if
you're going to read the verse that way, that right now there
has to be the ability to have kids and that's what puts
you in that category, אם כן, im ken, אין לך אשה שכשרה
ליבם. ein lecha isha she-keshera le-yabem. There's no woman that ever would
be in the category of יבום. yibum. Why not? שלא נעשה בעלה
סריס חמה שעה אחת קודם למיתתו. she-lo na'aseh ba'ala saris chamah sha'ah
achat kodem le-mitato. Because in the case of a natural death, the
guy's 80 or whatever he is, or he dies from illness, at
the five minutes before he dies he's probably not able, not fertile
in those last five minutes. Unless he got killed, well, it's true,
but anyway, okay. So therefore, and, so what would we say? Oh,
since your husband couldn't have kids, there's no מצוה mitzvah יבום. yibum.
Then there'll never be a מצוה mitzvah יבום. yibum. So what do
you see? You see you don't measure it by the last period
of time, like the most recently he couldn't have kids. You look
at it more big picture. So the- Big picture means you look
at the fact that earlier on he was able to have kids
and that's enough. So therefore, if that's true, that's consistent with רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that says you look at it big picture, and
if this person at one stage in his life was able to
have kids, then that would be enough to put him in the
category. Now of course, you could make a lot of distinctions. Number
one, you could say that okay, that's if earlier in the marriage
the guy could have had kids, not if some time in his
life before he even got married. Number one. Number two, that's as
far as the dead husband is concerned, that it's enough to say
well, maybe he theoretically could have had kids. But in terms of
the living brother who has a מצוות יבום mitzvah yibbum in order
to produce children, then you should say right now if you can't
have kids, why are you doing יבום? yibbum? Right? But the גמרא
Gemara says no, from this scenario of a minute before the guy
died he couldn't have kids, we're going to learn that we look
at it sort of more in terms of personal status and less
in terms of practically whether it was possible at that moment or
this moment. One minute, so let's see just what the גמרא Gemara
says.
So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי אליעזר פירוקא דרבא פירכא היא. Rebbe
Eliezer peruka deRava pircha hi. For רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer,
רבא's Rava answer is a question. Why? Because רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
says you don't go by שעת הכושר. shat hakosher. You don't go
by the fact that earlier in his life he could have kids.
You go by the fact that whether in theory he could heal
or not. So what does he do with רבא? Rava? Whether in
theory it's a סריס חמה sris chama he could heal, he could
get better. But the fact that earlier in his life he could
have kids isn't relevant. Well, how would he respond to רבא's Rava
point that every normal person who dies is in that category, so
why wouldn't that always be excluded, right?
So the גמרא Gemara says
no, התם ככחישותא דאתחלא ביה. hatam kichishuta de'atchala bei.
There it's not that he really is infertile, it's just that he's
dying. I don't exactly get the difference, but somehow he's fertile, but
maybe you know, he's not able right now to be consummating a
sex act with his wife, but that doesn't mean that the equipment
isn't in theoretically working. But once the equipment actually breaks down, you
know, then אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. So anyway, so that
was the גמרא's Gemara evidence that we don't look at things in
terms of the last minute we look big picture, but it's still
a big jump to go from there to say that A, that
if he was able before the marriage, that's enough to put him
in the category, and B, the surviving brother doesn't have to be
able to have kids as long as in some stage in his
life he was in the category. So this becomes a very what
I would call formalistic ruling that as long as the people are
in the category of somebody that at one stage could have kids,
you're not completely excluded, then the מצוות יבום mitzvah yibbum still applies
even if during this man's marriage kids wasn't a possibility and even
if the surviving brother now is unable to have children since in
some way they're still conceptually in the category, that's enough to say
the מצוות יבום mitzvah yibbum still applies. So there was a question
before, yeah. Who had the question? No, yeah.
Can't you also say the category was broader than just whether he
could actually have a kid in terms of the concept of raising
your brother's name? That it might just be by doing the יבום
yibbum even if there was no child produced from it?
I'm not remembering what you're referring to. That there's an idea of
להקים
שם le'hakim shem without the idea of a child?
Something that we discussed.
Oh, that we read the להקים שם le'hakim shem not going on
the child but going on which of the brothers, right? That is
true the way we reread some of those פסוקים psukim that it
was talking about the actual act of יבום yibbum and not so
much about the having the kid. You're right, maybe yeah, maybe that's
a factor in that. That's a good point. Maybe that's a factor
in that. Okay, yeah.
But either way, I mean, you know, they always say it's you
do חליצה chalitzah or something.
No, the גמרא Gemara before said that in theory you could do
יבום yibbum if we weren't talking about an
איסור issur of פצוע דכא. ptzua daka. It's just that we said
חליצה chalitzah just because רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer said it. But in
theory יבום yibbum is possible as well and the גמרא Gemara earlier
had a story of יבום. yibbum. I mean, maybe we would advise
against it but it certainly it seems like it's an option. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara has that idea that according to רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva a סריס אדם sris adam does חליצה chalitzah or
יבום yibbum because somehow he's still בגברא begavra in the category even
though practically you can't have להקים שם. le'hakim shem. And רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer says it would be by a סריס חמה sris chama
because even though he was never in the category but somehow maybe
we imagine that maybe somehow it could reverse itself. You know, it's
not like the actual there was an actual physical injury. Okay, so
let's take a look at that. So now the גמרא Gemara turns
to סריס חמה. sris chama. היכי דמי סריס חמה? Heichi dami sris
chama? What does this סריס חמה sris chama mean? What's the case?
אמר רבי יצחק בר רב יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן כל שלא ראה
שעה אחת בכשרותו.
Amar Rebbe Yitzchak bar Rav Yosef amar Rebbe Yochanan
kol shelo ra'ah sha'ah achat be'chashruto.
Somebody that never had the ability to have kids. Okay, because that's
why רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva puts it in that category. According to
רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, and therefore he's completely excluded. If somebody once
had the ability, then he would not be בגברא begavra excluded and
they'd be in the פרשה parsha and you would do יבום yibbum
or חליצה. chalitzah. So the גמרא Gemara says מידע ידעינן? mida yad'inan?
So how do we know that somebody can't have kids? Or how
do we know somebody was never for a moment had the ability?
But let's first start with how do you know that's true? אמר
אביי Amar Abaye כל המטיל מים ואין עושה כיפה. Kol hamatil mayim
ve'ein oseh kipa.
Somebody who when he urinates does not make an arc. The urine
doesn't sort of make an arc. So more like I guess dribbles
out, doesn't come in this powerful stream. That would be an indicator.
ממאי? Mimay? And if that was something that occurred, you know, even
when this kid was like six years old, so we would know
that this has been a permanent condition. This was not just a
temporary condition or something that happened later in life. ממה הוי? Mima
havay? How does somebody, how does that happen? How does somebody, how
does that condition develop? And remember if this is from the moment
that they were born, now we're going to look at the mother.
What happened when she was pregnant? So what does that come from?
דאפיה אמי בטיהרא. De'afya imei betihara. The mother baked bread in the
noonday sun. So therefore the heat of the oven and the heat
of the sun basically impacted her while she was pregnant. ושתיא שכרא.
Veshashtya shikra. And she didn't read the Surgeon General's warning and she
drank, and she drank mead and beer and intoxicating liquor, and that
מרקא marka like Rashi says it means like very, you know, either
mixed שכרא shikra or very strong שכרא, shikra, probably strong makes more
sense. Okay, anyway, so that led to this birth defect. So אמר
רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef היינו דשמענא לאמי דאמר כל שממעי אמו
לקי ולא ידענא מאי ניהו. Hainu deshmana le'Ami de'amar kol shemim'ei imo
laki velo yadana mai nihu.
So that's why I heard that Rav Ami said that
we're talking about anybody that from his mother's womb was already already
like injured, not injured, whatever, smitten. Yeah.
So anyway, ולא ידענא מאי ניהו, Velo yadana mai nihu, I didn't
know what he was referring to. And now I understand that he's
referring to identifying what a סריס חמה saris chama is. So the
גמרא Gemara says וליחוש שמא הברי בינתיים. Velichush shema hivri beintayim.
That's very nice that you saw that I don't know, when he
was six years old he had this urinating issue, but how do
you know that sometime between then and now he didn't have a
moment where he got better? A year, a day, or whatever. And
if that was true, his wife would be obligated in חליצה chalitza
or יבום yibum and you can't let her walk away, or he's
obligated to do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza to his brother's wife
and they can't walk away. Right? For because according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, if in one moment what a person was able to
do it, that puts him in the category. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so how do you know that? No, כיון דתחילתו וסופו לקי
לקי לא חיישינן. Keivan detichilaso vesofo laki laki lo chashinan.
Since we saw this when he was very young and we see
that this is the condition now, we're not concerned that somehow somewhere
between those two endpoints he actually recovered somewhere in the middle. We're
allowed to make a reasonable assumption that this has been a consistent
condition. So the גמרא Gemara says מתיב רב מרי. Mesiv Rav Mari.
So Rav Mari asked that רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר. Rabbi Chanina
ben Antignos omer. This is about a question about a type of
a condition in the eye of a בכור bechor animal that whether
it's considered a מום mum or not in order to, you know,
allow it not to be brought as a קרבן. korban. So what
do we teach there? בודקין אותו שלש פעמים בתוך שמונים יום. Bodkin
oso shalosh pe'amim besoch shemonim yom.
You check the בכור, bechor, the firstborn animal, three times
during eighty days to see if it still has this condition in
the eye. So you check it beginning of eighty days, middle, and
the end. So you don't just do the two endpoints. You at
least need some check in the middle and that's only over eighty
days to be able to assume that this condition has been continuous.
So how come here we can assume just with the two endpoints?
So the גמרא Gemara says לחד אבר חיישינן לכולא גופה לא חיישינן.
Lechad evar chashinan lechula gufa lo chashinan. If
it's a condition of just one limb, then you think that maybe,
you know, maybe it got better in the middle. If it's a
condition that affects the whole body, it's more systemic, then somehow we
assume it's much less likely that it just reversed itself.
We don't consider
the סריס saris one limb? Yeah, I know. Apparently, it's interesting, we
assume not. I mean, maybe because we assume that we don't see
any actual physical injury to those body parts and it's a condition
somebody is born with, so we assume it has to do something
more with something, you know, systemic, right? You know, rather than something
about the physical, you know, the physical condition of that particular body
part. So therefore anyway, because it's something that's more systemic, we're not
going to assume, it's going to be, we're going to assume it's
less likely that it reversed itself. Okay? So just knowing beginning and
end is enough. But this shows you what emerges from רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that would say even one minute having been fit puts
the person in the category. Okay, that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position.
רבי אליעזר אומר חולץ. Rabbi Eliezer omer choleitz. Rabbi Eliezer says no,
it's the reverse. A סריס חמה, saris chama, somebody who's born with
a condition and it's not based on some anatomical thing, you know,
sort of injury, is something that we think could reverse itself and
that person is in the category. Again, even though he won't be
having kids, but in the, you know, in the category and therefore
you do יבום yibum and חליצה, chalitza, whereas a סריס אדם saris
adam you do not because that's not reversible. So the גמרא Gemara
says ורמינהו, Uremihu, I'll ask you on this idea that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says a סריס חמה saris chama does חליצה chalitza and
a סריס אדם saris adam does not. Here we have a teaching
בן עשרים שנה ולא הביא שתי שערות. Ben esrim shana velo heivi
shtei se’aros. And now we're going to start getting into identifying how
you know somebody's a סריס saris because a סריס saris again is
not just somebody that, you know, hasn't had kids, like again, is,
you know, infertile, actually as we've been talking about that there's real
seen as something very much about either... So we have a case
of בן עשרים שנה ולא הביא שתי שערות ben esrim shana velo
hevi shtei searos and now we're going to start getting into identifying
how you know somebody's a סריס saris because a סריס saris again
is not just somebody that hasn't had kids, is infertile. Actually, we've
been talking about that there's really seen as something very much about
either some physical injury or very much about the person's some type
of a systemic condition. So let's take a look. בן עשרים שנה
ולא הביא שתי שערות ben esrim shana velo hevi shtei searos if
somebody has already turned to be 20 years and has not had
two pubic hairs, יביא ראיה שהוא בן עשרים yavi raya shehu ben
esrim bring proof that you're 20 years old, והוא סריס vehu saris
and that person is considered the category of סריס saris now. Meaning
that the גמרא Gemara here assumes that a סריס חמה, saris chama,
somebody who has this systemic condition, is somebody that never really has
pubic hairs, never gets those secondary sex
characteristics. And so again, it really shows that we're not just talking
about inability, like infertile. There's something much more systemic going on in
terms of this. This person never actually reaches physical maturity in terms
of sexual maturity. So therefore, he won't get pubic hairs. So how
does this person ever halachically become an adult since for an adult
you need to be 13 and have two pubic hairs? So if
you're 20 and don't have the pubic hairs, then we assume it
must be you're already 20 years old. It's not just that your
maturity is delayed; it's that it's not actually happening because you must
be in this category of סריס saris that is never going to
reach physical maturity. And therefore you're an adult once you hit 20
even without the pubic hairs once we've categorized you as a סריס.
saris. The גמרא's Gemara going to say later on that the phrase
הוא הסריס hu hasaris does not just mean, aha, because you're 20
without pubic hairs we know you're a סריס, saris, it actually means
there are also other physical indicators that put you in the סריס
saris category. Lack of facial hair, smooth skin, we're going to talk
about other things that are going to show other ways in which
there's lack of the body, the physical maturity of the body.
Do you need to just look at facial hair, be one or
the other?
Well we'll see, it's both actually, not שתי שערות shtei searos plus
other indicators. Okay, so once that person hits 20, doesn't have שתי
שערות shtei searos and as we'll see later has other indicators, they're
in the category of סריס. saris. Now that's obviously סריס חמה, saris
chama, because סריס אדם saris adam is just something that happens to
the genitals. This is actually something that is more about the whole
body. Okay, so that person is in the
סריס saris category, הוא הסריס, hu hasaris, and once you're a סריס,
saris, a) you're an adult once you hit that, but b) לא
חולץ ולא מיבם, lo choletz velo meyabem, you're out of the category
of חליצה ויבום. chalitza veyibum. That's like, right, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
that says סריס חמה saris chama is out of the category of
חליצה ויבום. chalitza veyibum.
לא חולץ ולא מיבם. lo choletz velo meyabem. Now what if it's
a woman? בת עשרים ולא הביאה שתי שערות, bas esrim velo hevia
shtei searos, similar הלכה, halacha, 20 years and she, a woman, and
she doesn't have two pubic hairs, תביא ראיה שהיא בת עשרים, tavi
raya shehi bas esrim, bring proof that she's 20 years old, והיא
אילונית, vehi ailonis, and then she is the case of אילונית. ailonis.
Again, not just an infertile woman, an אילונית ailonis is not an
עקרה. akara. An עקרה akara actually, again, ironically, there would be a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום וחליצה yibum vechalitza if a woman was infertile.
I mean, I guess in our history we have plenty of infertile
women who had children later in life. But anyway, but this is
somebody that's like, again, systemic, it's about their whole
body. And therefore that person is an אילונית. ailonis. That's the type
of woman that's excluded from חליצה ויבום. chalitza veyibum. Once she is
20 without pubic hairs, now she's considered an adult, לא חולצת ולא
מתיבמת, lo choletzes velo misyabemes, but she's out of the category of
חליצה chalitza and יבום. yibum. דברי בית הלל, divrei Beis Hillel, these
are the words of בית הלל Beis Hillel that go by the
age of
20. ובית שמאי אומרים, uBeis Shammai omrim, זה וזה בן שמונה עשרה,
zeh vizeh ben shmoneh esre, no you go by 18, same basic
principle, just 18 and not
20. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, הזכר כדברי בית הלל והנקבה
כדברי בית שמאי. hazachar kedivrei Beis Hillel vehanekeva kedivrei Beis Shammai. Males
you go to 20, females you go by
18, because women mature before men and therefore you can determine their
status at an earlier age. Anyway, what is the challenge? The problem
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is buying into the definitions here of
סריס, saris, he's just debating the issues of 18 or 20, and
he presumably he's buying into what the ברייתא braita says is the
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. The נפקא מינה nafka mina is that no
חליצה chalitza no יבום. yibum. But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in our
משנה Mishna says that a סריס חמה saris chama does חליצה ויבום.
chalitza veyibum. And here it says a סריס חמה saris chama doesn't
do חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum. So what's the story?
All right,
so the גמרא Gemara will say that. But let's see what the
question is. It sounds like he agrees that a סריס חמה saris
chama doesn't do חליצה ויבום. chalitza veyibum. So אמר רמי בר דקולי
אמר שמואל חזר בו רבי אליעזר, amar Rami bar Dikuli amar Shmuel
chazar bo Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer reversed himself. Now, right,
you're right, it contradicts. So one of these, he didn't hold by
one of these statements. So the גמרא Gemara wants to know which
one did he reverse himself. מאי האי הדר ביה, mai hai hadar
beh, which one did he retract? תא שמע דתניא, ta shema detanya,
we have a ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, סריס
חמה, saris chama, somebody who is a סריס חמה saris chama again
born with this condition, חולץ וחולצין לאשתו, choletz vecholtzim leishto, he does
חליצה chalitza and you do חליצה chalitza with his wife, again, like
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says in our משנה, Mishna, he does do
חליצה, chalitza, שכן במינן מתרפאין באלכסנדריה של מצרים, sheken beminan misrapin beAlexandria
shel Mitzrayim, because people with this condition get better in Alexandria in
Egypt. Maybe they've got some, they know what treatment to give the
person, right, major medical center of the ancient world. So that's why
he says in our משנה, Mishna, right, שיש לו רפואה. sheyesh lo
refua. Now that the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like... that he
reversed this, he reversed the position that we just quoted, that he's
excluded from חליצה chalitzah and יבום, yibum, and he held by the
position in our משנה mishna that he does. So, how does it
prove it? You know, is it so A you could say it's
two against one, we've got our משנה mishna and this ברייתא braita
that says that he does חליצה, chalitzah, so that assumes that that
was his more, his second opinion. Of course, who knows, maybe there
was just two quotes from his earlier opinion. How do you know
which one was his earlier, which one was his later? So רש"י
Rashi also says because he says specifically that they, that we know
that these people can be healed in Alexandria. Wasn't just hypothetically, oh,
maybe they'll get better. Since he had very concrete knowledge that there
was, you know, that these people could get healed in Alexandria, that
would be the position that he would presumably hold by and not
reverse himself by, based on that very concrete evidence. So that's what
he's saying. Yes, there's this other statement that he said that he
doesn't do חליצה, chalitzah, but he reversed, but he abandoned that position.
He holds like he said in the משנה, mishna, he does חליצה
chalitzah because in theory he can get better. Okay, רבי אלעזר אומר,
Rabbi Elazar omer,
don't get confused, this isn't Rabbi Eliezer, it's רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
says לעולם לא הדר ביה. l'olam lo hadar bei. Rabbi Elazar did
not reverse himself. וכי תנן ההיא לעונשין איתמר. V'chitnan hahee l'onshin itmar.
Okay,
and like Michael said, when Rabbi Eliezer said in that discussion of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, you go eighteen
for a girl and twenty for a boy, he's not agreeing to
the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. The גמרא Gemara there, the ברייתא braita
there is giving the נפקא מינה nafka mina of whether you do
חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum. Rabbi Eliezer says as far as I'm
concerned, a סריס sris always does חליצה chalitzah and יבום. yibum. But
you have to determine when somebody's a סריס sris for other הלכות,
halachot, when they're an adult, when they would get punished in a
בית דין. beis din. Normally an adult would be thirteen or twelve
for punishment in a בית דין. beis din. This person who hasn't
brought pubic hairs would be an adult later at eighteen or twenty.
So I'm debating when to give the, when the person is considered
a סריס sris or an אילונית, ailonit, but I don't agree with
your נפקא מינה. nafka mina. I think a סריס sris and an
אילונית ailonit does חליצה chalitzah and יבום, yibum, but there are other
places it matters whether one does.
Doesn't maturity matter for עונשין? onshin? I mean, that's the bigger question.
In other words, why can't we just say it's emotional maturity?
Yeah, I don't know, that's a bigger question. Okay. So anyway, but
both of these positions agree, by the way, whether he was הדר
ביה hadar bei or לא הדר ביה, lo hadar bei, they agree
that he holds that a סריס חמה sris chama does חליצה chalitzah
and יבום. yibum. That the statement where he said, the discussion about
eighteen and twenty where it says does not, either he abandoned that
statement, he reversed himself, or he never meant it, he never meant
that he doesn't do. So Rabbi Eliezer still very clearly holds he
does חליצה chalitzah and יבום, yibum, but the question is again now
the issue about at what age does somebody become a סריס. sris.
And now we're going to discuss that. So let's take a look.
Okay, לעונשין. l'onshin. Now, אכל חלב מבן שתים עשרה. achal chelev m'ben
shtem esrei. Now we're going to discuss so that we figured out
Rabbi Eliezer, he didn't reverse himself, and now we're figuring out this
issue about that a person becomes a סריס sris at the age
of twenty. So let's take a look. אכל חלב מבן שתים עשרה
achal chelev m'ben shtem esrei ויום אחד עד בן שמונה עשרה. v'yom
echad ad ben shmoneh esrei. So somebody actually here for some reason
we're talking about a girl because it's eighteen, presumably we're talking within
Rabbi Elazar, anywhere about בן בת, ben bat, right? Yeah, I know,
so it should have been בת. bat. But anyway, so anyway, but
okay, this woman eats חלב, chelev, does this sin, after she's twelve
years and a day, which had she had pubic hairs she'd be
an adult, but she doesn't have pubic hairs so she's not an
adult, until she's eighteen years old.
ונולדו בה סימני סריס. V'noldu bah simanei sris. And then she has
the signs of being a סריס, sris, she doesn't have pubic hairs,
she has other signs which we'll get to, and she's deemed to
be a סריס, sris, or an אילונית ailonit really. לאחר מכאן הביא
שתי שערות. L'achar mikan hevi shtei sa'arot. It's again, it's funny the
mixing of male and female here. Right? Maybe it's male, there's already
two or three? I know, but רש"י Rashi also says the twelve
and the eighteen point to the fact that it's female. I don't
know what to do. Anyway, לאחר מכאן הביא שתי שערות. l'achar mikan
hevi shtei sa'arot. And then she brings two pubic hairs. I'm going
to bracket the לאחר מכאן l'achar mikan in a minute because that's
a little confusing. Let's even just deal with the fact that this
person basically did a sin between twelve and eighteen, or thirteen and
twenty, and then was identified to be a סריס. sris. Turned eighteen,
no pubic hairs, other סימנים simanim of a סריס sris identified to
be a סריס. sris. What's the הלכה? halacha? רב אמר נעשה סריס
למפרע. Rav amar na'aseh sris l'mafreia.
So now that we see that they're eighteen or twenty and no
pubic hairs and other סימנים, simanim, we know they're a סריס, sris,
and here's the question: so when were they an adult from? Retroactively
from the age of twelve? Do we say, yeah, we assumed when
you weren't bringing pubic hairs you had delayed puberty, and then you
would become an adult when you were fifteen and had pubic hairs,
right? But now we see it wasn't delayed puberty. Now we see
you were never going to hit puberty. You're a סריס. sris. Oh,
you're a סריס, sris, so maybe you're an adult from the age
of twelve or the age of thirteen. Or does a סריס sris
only become an adult from the age of eighteen or twenty? Okay,
so we know you're a סריס sris at the age of eighteen
or twenty. When do you, when do you become identified now that
we know that's the status as having been an adult? So רב
אמר נעשה סריס למפרע, Rav amar na'aseh sris l'mafreia,
retroactively we now know you were a סריס sris from the age
of twelve or thirteen and you're חייב chayav for those עבירות aveiros
that you did. שמואל אמר קטן היה באותה שעה, Shmuel amar katan
haya be'osa sha'a, no, you were a minor and you only become
identified as an adult when we identify you as a סריס saris
at the age of 18 or 20. So that would be just
a simple case where what's the normal הלכה, halacha, when does a
person, once they hit the age of 20, retroactively are they an
adult retroactively? So we actually add the other complicating factor is לאחר
מכאן הביא שתי שערות la'achar mikan heivi shtei se'aros to tell you
the following: You might say that if this person after was identified
as a סריס saris at the age of 18 and then had
pubic hairs, that might even be more of a reason to assume
that we'll make you an adult at the later stage. Because if
now you have pubic hairs at the age of 24, we say,
oh, well actually maybe there was an element of delayed puberty going
on. It wasn't just the סריס saris idea. So now maybe all
the more we should say you only become an adult at the
later stage, not the earlier stage. And even there, רב Rav says
that retroactively you were סריס saris from the age of 12 or
13. Okay, so that's why the גמרא Gemara added that factor that
the pubic hairs came later to say even with that other thing
that's pushing you to say that it's delayed puberty and you should
be an adult at the later stage, רב Rav is saying no,
once you're 18 or 20 and identified as a סריס, saris, even
if pubic hairs come later, I will still say that once you're
that's your category, you are an adult from the age of 12
or 13.
Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara says that you become an adult
once you get the pubic hair?
No, he would say you become an adult once you once you
hit once you get the סימנים simanim even earlier. So the pubic
hair is just another thing that should have pushed us later. But
nobody is saying that it pushed.
רב Rav is saying let's say you got these 24 and until
then you didn't have anything. So רב Rav is saying that you
are an
adult from the age of 12 or 13.
ושל שמואל ve-shel Shmuel is saying
you're an adult from the age of 20. Yeah. Okay, so the
pubic hair doesn't change that, nobody's saying we reassess and say you
weren't a סריס, saris, right, which you could have thought. Nobody is
saying that, but the point is it would have pushed you for
a later date and nevertheless רב Rav is saying an earlier date.
By the way, the נפקא מינה's nafka mina might not only be
for עונש. onesh. Let's say somebody engaged in a financial transaction during
that period, right, would we nullify it or not because we would
say the person wasn't an adult? So again, רב Rav would say
that no, retroactively the person does become an adult from the age
of
בר/בת מצוה, Bar/Bas Mitzva, yes.
So if the person has pubic hairs at 24, does that mean
he's going to be able to have children?
Oh, I don't know.
Does it change the status?
Yeah, so like I said, that complicates it and then you could
say maybe we would reassess maybe the person wouldn't have been a
סריס saris at all. That the גמרא—at Gemara least the גמרא Gemara
isn't getting into that. רש"י Rashi also sort of brackets that. רש"י
Rashi says like we're not reassessing the person's status as a סריס,
saris, it just would have been another factor that would have pushed
us to look at it later rather than earlier. Okay, so now
the—so but that complicates it. The basic question is, is it retroactive
or not? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתקיף ליה רב
יוסף לרב. Maskif leh Rav Yosef leh Rav. So רב יוסף Rav
Yosef challenged רב. Rav. אילונית לרבי מאיר יהא קנס.
Ailonis le-Rabbi Meir
yehei knas. So רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir of the position in כתובות,
Kesubos, the next מסכתא masechta we're going to go to, that an
if a woman is raped or seduced, right, then there's this whole
idea of paying the קנס, knas, 50 shekel. And the תורה Torah
talks about a נערה, na'ara, about a lass. Somebody who is between
12 and 12 and a half, between the two pubic hairs till
six months after. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it does not apply
to a קטנה, ketana, right, there's a question: is a נערה na'ara
to exclude just a בוגרת, bogeres, an older woman, or is it
to even exclude a younger woman, a קטנה? ketana? So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says it does not apply to a קטנה. ketana. And
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says an אילונית ailonis doesn't get a קנס,
knas, cause an אילונית ailonis is like a קטנה ketana until she
even when she hits בת מצוה, bas mitzvah, she's still a קטנה,
ketana, she has no pubic hairs, she remains a קטנה, ketana, and
then when she hits 20 or 18, then she becomes a בוגרת.
bogeres. So she'll never have a קנס. knas. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara is saying, wait one minute. According to רב Rav that retroactively
she became an adult at the age of 12, then why shouldn't
she have a קנס knas from the age of 12 to 12
and a half, if retroactively we go back to the age of
12? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye,
no, מקטנותא נפקא לבוגר. mi-katnusa nafka le-voger.
Even if you retroactively go back to the age of 12, she
never has נערות. na'aros. נערות na'aros comes when you have pubic hairs.
This woman retroactively went back so at 11 days and the day
before her בת מצוה bat mitzvah she was a קטנה, ketana, and
now we see retroactively when she hit her בת מצוה bat mitzvah
she became a גדולה, gedola, a בוגרת. bogeres. She never had a
period of נערות. na'aros. A period of נערות na'aros is only by
a natural case of puberty of maturity, okay? So whereas according to
שמואל, Shmuel, right, so here's the case, right? Here she hits 12,
here she hits 18, and here you have סימני simanei right, אילונית
ailonis or whatever or סריס, saris, okay? So according to שמואל, Shmuel,
at this stage we've identified, right, that she is, so according to
שמואל Shmuel she becomes a גדולה gedola here
and until this point she's been a קטנה, ketana, okay? That's what
שמואל Shmuel would say, okay? This would be, yeah, שמואל. Shmuel. And
according to רב, Rav, רב Rav would say, no, רב Rav would
say once you've hit this point you jump back here and you
say that at this moment she became a גדולה, gedola, a בוגרת,
bogeres, but still she became a גדולה, gedola, she became a בוגרת,
bogeres, and until... so that she was a קטנה. ketanah. So there's
no period of נערות, na'arus, okay? Right? For a normal, for a
normal girl between twelve and twelve and a half, right, is when
you're a נערה, na'arah, okay? That's for a normal girl. But that's
when you have normal, you know, pubic hairs, normal maturing body, so
that maturing period is when you're a נערה. na'arah. So here the
גמרא Gemara says this isn't the problem, whether according to רב, Rav,
whether according to שמואל, Shmuel, an אילונית ailonis goes straight from being
a קטנה ketanah to a גדולה, gedolah, to a בוגרת. bogeret. There's
no נערות na'arus period. נערות Na'arus is when the body is naturally
maturing. The only question is, does she make the transition on her
18th birthday or does she make the transition on her 12th birthday?
And what was the purpose of this
קנס?
knas? Whatever, the general קנס knas in the תורה Torah about אונס
ones and מפתה. mefateh. For what? I'm not, let's not talk about
that now. Yes?
So by hitting puberty later, you're considering her an adult woman earlier,
as in...
Yes! By hitting puberty late—well, she never hits puberty. By never having
had puberty...
Right. Exactly, exactly. Okay.
So now it says like
this, אמר ליה—so Amar leih רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back, כל
כי הני מילתא מעלייתא יסממו משמיא. Kol ki hanei milta maalyata yisammemu
mishmaya. Oh, such a brilliant answer! All other good answers like this,
I should take credit for. This
is like your classic, you know, graduate professor. If the student says
a good answer, I should take credit for those good answers. Okay.
ותניא, Ve-tanya, and we taught like this in a ברייתא: braisa: אין
סריס נידון כבן סורר ומורה. Ein saris nidon ke-ben sorer u-moreh. Similarly,
a סריס saris can't be a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh
because a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh is also from the
period of בר מצוה bar mitzvah for a few months after, right?
So this,
see, or actually there's another reason: לפי שאין בן סורר ומורה נידון
אלא בחתימת זקן—or Lefi she-ein ben sorer u-moreh nidon ela be-chasimas zakan
התחתון—because ha-tachton a בן סורר ומורה—excuse ben sorer u-moreh me, right, because
a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh can only be somebody that
has his like lower pubic hair and that would never be the
case of a סריס. saris. So for that reason, he's out of
the category. ואין אילונית נידונית כנערה מאורסה. Ve-ein ailonis nidonis ke-na'arah me'orasah.
An אילונית ailonis is not in the נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah category,
which is also a special עונש onesh for a case of adultery
of a נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. She never becomes a נערה, na'arah,
שמקטנותה יצאה לדרגא—she she-mikatnusah yatz'ah le-darga never, she jumps over, leapfrogs over
the נערה na'arah status. Okay. I mean, the בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer u-moreh is similar to what I was saying. It's a similar
concept of נערות na'arus that we have by a male, but it's
not as much of an identified label as we have by a
female, which we call it a status of נערה. na'arah. Okay. And
anyway, so both a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh and a,
so both a man and a woman jumped over that maturing status
right after בר bar and בת מצוה bas mitzvah and therefore they're
excluded from these categories. Okay. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, said
רבי אבהו: Rabbi Abbahu: Now we get to the identifying characteristics in
addition to the lack of pubic hair. סימני סריס ואילונית ובן שמונה
אין עושים בהם מעשה עד שיהיו בן עשרים. Simanei saris ve-ailonis u-ben
shemonah ein osim bahem ma'aseh ad she-yihyu ben esrim.
So somebody has these indicators of being a סריס saris or an
אילונית, ailonis, meaning no pubic hair, other indicators that we're going to
get to. I'll get to them in a minute.
Or somebody is born in the eighth month. Completely different category. But
the issue about somebody being born in the eighth month of pregnancy
is the גמרא Gemara assumes that such a child would die and
therefore the person cannot be considered to have a חזקת חיה chazakas
chayah to assume to be viable until they hit their 20th birthday.
So these are two categories of people that the 20th birthday matters.
So I was born in the eighth month, so when I hit
my 20th birthday, I made a party for being חזקת חיה. chazakas
chayah. Really?
No, actually nowadays we assess these הלכות halachos of eighth month very
differently nowadays. Anyway,
so both of these categories of people you need to hit twenty
years to determine what their status is.
Does he have any הלכתית halachic significance at thirteen, a בן שמונה?
ben shemonah?
No, he does, but it's not like he's not an adult. It's
just that he doesn't have a חזקת חיה chazakas chayah for other
types of הלכה, halacha, okay? As we'll see in a minute what
one aspect of the הלכה halacha would be. Anyway, so these people
that you have to wait... so all these people, אין עושים בהם
מעשה עד שיהיו בן עשרים. ein osim bahem ma'aseh ad she-yihyu ben
esrim. You wait until they're twenty before, meaning even though this person
is nineteen and he looks healthy and he's run the Olympics and
he does the marathon or whatever, no, he doesn't have a חזקת
חיה chazakas chayah until twenty. You can't make a final determination of
a status, even though this person clearly looks like a סריס saris
or אילונית ailonis and has all these indicators that they're not having
natural type of, you know, physical maturity and puberty and so on.
No, you cannot determine that that's their status in terms of יבום
yibum or חליצה chalitzah or other types of הלכה halacha until they
actually hit twenty. You need to hit twenty, okay? So then now
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, to discuss a little bit
about בן שמונה ben shemonah and then talk about what those indicators
are. ובן שמונה מי חיי? U-ben shemonah mi chayei? Does somebody who's
eight months old actually live? Like how can they live even until
twenty? How do they ever make it to twenty? That's impossible, nobody
ever makes it to twenty if they were born in their eighth
month. So the גמרא Gemara says, והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braisa: בן שמונה הרי הוא כאבן, Ben shemonah harei hu ke-even,
an eight-month baby born in the eighth month is like a stone,
ואסור לטלטלו, ve-asur letaltelo, and the mother can't even pick him up
on שבת, Shabbos, he's מוקצה. muktzah. He's considered like somebody like already
dead. It's pretty radical.
but what the mother can do is she can't pick him up
to nurse him, but she can lean over him and he can
nurse himself, or some say, but he's מוקצה muktzah מפני הסכנה mipnei
hasakanah
because without nursing it'll be a danger to the mother and maybe
also to him, but you know obviously the question is what would
you be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos to save his life? It sounds
like in the גמרא Gemara you wouldn't. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara
sounds like my God, this guy is definitely going to die. How
could we how could you be talking about an idea that he
lives till 20 since when would anybody live till 20 in this
scenario? So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai
askinan now there's this whole question here about the גרסא, girsa, we'll
read it with our גרסא, girsa, כשגמרו סימניו. keshegamru simanav.
It's a case where actually the, you know, the physical characteristics when
he was born, even though he was born in the eighth month,
were at a certain stage of completion. His hair, his fingernails, other
types of things which indicate that this child might not really be
a technical eighth-month baby. He might be a seventh-month baby that's a
holdover. This is again the ironic position of the גמרא Gemara which
says that a baby born in the seventh month is viable, a
baby born in the eighth month is not viable. Ah, don't we
see as so much traditional about what you sort of saw about
traditional societies, you know, you had these beliefs, and this wasn't just
religious beliefs, you know, and then some any empirical evidence that contradicted
it, you found a way to explain away rather than to reassess
your beliefs. So like not like any of that ever happens nowadays.
But okay. Anyway, anyway,
so we see eighth-month babies that survived? No, no, no, those are
seventh-month babies that were just delayed in being born. Okay, so
I don't understand, why does an eighth-month baby and the other's a
seventh-month baby that took two weeks late to be born? I don't
know. Anyway, so and that's why that baby survived. How do you
know? Because you can see, you know, the fingernails are more complete,
the hair is more complete. That shows that that was one of
those viable babies that was just born a little bit later. Okay,
דתניא detanya like we saw in the ברייתא beraita איזהו בן שמונה
eizehu ben shemonah what's a בן שמונה? ben shemonah? כל שלא כלו
לו חדשיו kol shelo kalu lo chodashav
the months have not been complete, it doesn't have, you know, it's
not a full nine months. רבי אומר סימנים מוכיחים עליו. Rabbi omer
simanim mochiachin alav. No, you can actually there are physical characteristics. שערו
וצפרניו שלא גמרו. searo vetzipernav shelo gamru. The hair and the fingernails
are not complete. So if somebody has hair and fingernails that is
complete, even if they're born in the eighth month, they might be
a seventh-month a holdover from the seventh-month. Of course, it seems like
even then you need to wait till twenty to to to verify
that, right? And that's his חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that
even if somebody has סימני סריס, simanei saris, you can't determine their
status till twenty. Even if somebody looks like they were born viable,
if they were born in the eighth month, you can't determine their
status until they hit twenty. Okay, now based on this idea of
a holdover, we have a shocking next statement. אלא
הא דעבד ela ha de-avad I'm sorry first גמרא Gemara finishes its
thought. טעמא דלא גמרו taama delo gamru the reason is that those
the hair and the nails weren't complete. הא גמרו ha gamru if
they were complete אמינא האי בר שבע הוא ואשתהויי דאשתהי. amina hai
bar sheva hu ve-ishtahui de-ishtahi. And this is a seven-month-old baby that
got held over. Okay, so
therefore even though there's indicators that this child is viable, we wait
till the age of twenty before finalizing it. Even though there are
indicators that this person is a סריס, saris, we wait till the
age of twenty before finalizing it. Now that we've introduced this idea
of a holdover, here's an interesting הלכה. halacha. אלא הא דעבד רבא
תוספאה ela ha de-avad Rava Tosfaah
that which רבא תוספאה Rava Tosfaah did, עובדא באשה שהלך בעלה למדינת
הים uvda be-ishah she-halach baalah limdinat hayam
a woman whose husband went to a, you know, to a foreign
country, went overseas, ואשתהיה תריסר ירחי שתא ve-ishtehi tressar yarchei shata
she waited twelve months after the husband departed, she had a baby.
Okay, so whose baby you think it was? I would imagine not
the husband's. ואכשריה ve-achshreih
and he said that the baby was כשר, kasher, wasn't a ממזר.
mamzer. How could he do that? כמאן keman who is this going
like? So כרבי דאמר משתהה ke-Rabbi de-amar mishtahai this must be like
רבי, Rabbi, right? רבי Rabbi said that you could have a baby
that was a seven-month-old baby that was held over in the womb.
So therefore, right, for two weeks. So therefore, if you could have
a seven-month-old baby that was held over in the womb, you could
have a nine-month baby that's held over for three months. So this
baby was born after twelve months really was the husband's child, just
took three months late late to be born. So that's going
כרבי דאמר משתהה. ke-Rabbi de-amar mishtahai. Is that only going like רבי
Rabbi who says that the baby is held over, which is okay,
maybe yes, but maybe they wanted it to be just like that
דעת יחיד. daas yachid. So the גמרא Gemara says no. כיון דאיכא
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר משתהה keivan de-ika Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
de-amar mishtahai it wasn't just רבי Rabbi that hold believes that babies
could get held held over in the womb. There's also רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and therefore he was going like
that majority position. Which is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel דתניא detanya we saw in a ברייתא beraita רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר כל ששהה שלשים יום באדם אינו נפל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer kol she-shaha sheloshim yom ba-adam eino nefel
that if somebody if a baby was,
a minute, let
me
just double check רש"י, Rashi, hold on.
Right, so if a baby is born, and this משתהה mishtahai is
not in the womb. If a baby is born and survives thirty
days. Then we assume that you don't need to wait till they're
twenty, then even if it's born in the seventh month or in
the eighth month, we assume that this child is not a נפל.
nefel. A child is born in the eighth month, we do not
have to wait till they hit twenty, if they just survive for
a month after being born, they're no longer a נפל, nefel, they're
considered to be to be viable. So what does that show? Why
are they viable? They're born in the eighth month. So again, it
shows that presumably he agrees to this idea that a baby could
be born in the eighth month and have been held over from
their seventh month.
Why can't it just be a nine month baby born early?
I don't know, it's good because that's what an eight month baby
is, I don't know. Anyway, who knows? Anyway, the idea that you
could have a baby that was held over. What?
Is there something magical about eight months, the number?
I have no idea.
What? What are you saying?
I know, I mean the interesting question is was this a belief
held in the larger world outside of the Jewish world at that
time, you know? I've never researched that.
In a Darwinian sense, you don't want to put your resources into
a baby that's going to die. Stop nursing.
All right,
all right, that's pretty hard. But then seventh month you don't say
that, which I don't understand.
Yeah, maybe I'm not sure what to attribute that to. מה אומר
שטיינזלץ? Mah omer Steinsaltz? שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz
says
it doesn't specify, but some other legal systems recognize pregnancies even longer
than one year. Okay, there you go. So I mean look, for
ממזר mamzer you could say it's a nice legal fiction, you know,
I mean, you know, we've dealt already, we've started dealing with some
degrees of legal fictions before. Well, you know, any ממזר mamzer would
have died out, so we don't have to worry that there are
ממזרים mamzerim around that we don't know about. Anyway, okay, but here
at least you see that in terms of this idea, it's not
just רבי, Rebbi, there are other opinions out there that a baby
could be born in the eighth month and be viable, you know,
once he hits twenty years and once he hits a month, slight
difference there, but anyway, and assumed to be a seven month old
baby that's held over. Now back to our idea about the סימני
סריס. simanei saris. So one thing we talked about is no pubic
hairs, we've talked about hitting the age of twenty, but we've also
been talking about סימני סריס. simanei saris. And now we're going to
get to what those סימנים simanim are. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, איזהו
סריס חמה? eizehu saris chama? What a case of סריס חמה? saris
chama? כל שבן עשרים ולא הביא שתי שערות, kol sheben esrim v'lo
heivi shtei searot, we've already talked about that, twenty without two pubic
hairs. ואפילו הביא לאחר מכאן, v'afillu heivi l'achar mikan, and here's the
issue that we were alluding to before, even if those pubic hairs
appear later, הרי הוא כסריס לכל דבריו, harei hu k'saris l'chol devarav,
that does not lead to a reassessing of his condition, of his
status, once he's twenty without pubic hairs, he's considered a סריס saris
regardless of later pubic hairs. ואפילו הביא לאחר מכאן. v'afillu heivi l'achar
mikan.
So he can never get out of the status?
Correct. Although it's an interesting question because you know, the what's-his-name, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said that the סריס חמה saris chama is somebody
who could be healed in Greater Alexandria in Egypt. So maybe just
the existence of pubic hairs is not enough to reassess. I don't
know, I don't know what would be enough to reassess. Get a
note from your doctor in Alexandria, but not the pubic hairs. Okay.
סו הרי הוא כסריס לכל דבריו. So harei hu k'saris l'chol devarav.
ואלו הן סימניו, v'eilu hen simanav, and here are the additional signs.
כל שאין לו זקן, kol she'ein lo zakan, anybody that does not
have a beard, presumably that means a beard on the chin, not
pubic hair. We already mentioned no pubic hair. ושערו לקוי, v'sa'aro lakui,
has, you know, his hair is
whatever,
smitten is not a good word. Anyway, ושערו... v'sa'aro... Smooth. Well, I
don't know, I don't know if it means thin hair on the
head or it means like not having body hair. No hair. The
funny phrase לקוי. lakui. What? Affected. Affected. Affected his hair. But how
is it affected?
As you'd mean it would be say be כרת.
kares. What? Soft? Like downy type of hair? Again, I also don't
know if it means hair on the scalp or hair on the
body. Soft,
okay. ובשרו מחליק, u'vesaro machlik, like a smooth skin. רש״י... Rashi...
these are like more like feminine sort of... the body has more
feminine type of characteristics, seems to be the point.
That wouldn't work for a girl though. What?
That would work... well right. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר משום רבי
יהודה בן יאיר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben
Yair, כל שאין מימיו מעלין רתיחו. kol she'ein meimav ma'alin retichu. So
hair... so anything that the urine does not like steam when a
person urinates, which the steam that happens from urine is I think
it's because it's coming from...
Isn't it your foam?
Oh foam, oh okay, that's interesting. ויש אומרים, v'yesh omrim, right, ויש
אומרים כל המטיל
מים ואין עושה כיפה, v'yesh omrim kol hamatil mayim v'ein ose kipah,
like we mentioned before, when he urines it doesn't make an arch.
ויש אומרים כל ששכבת זרעו דוחה, v'yesh omrim kol sheshichvat zaro dacha,
when the semen is more like liquidy and not viscous. ויש אומרים
כל שמי רגליו מחמיצים, v'yesh omrim kol shemei raglav machmitzim, any that
the urine does not become like stench or smelly. אחרים אומרים, Acherim
omrim, others say, כל שרוחץ בימות הגשמים ואין בשרו מעלה הבל, kol
sherocheitz biyemot hageshamim v'ein besaro ma'aleh hevel, anybody that showers in the
winter and the body doesn't give off a steam. So I mean
something obviously going around with the body heat issue. Okay, רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר כל שקולו לקוי, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer kol
shekolo lakui, here's again that לקוי, lakui, anybody that's sound is... That's
voice is affected, is not a natural voice, ואין ניכר בין איש
לאשה ve'ein nikar bein ish le'isha and high pitch, and you wouldn't
be able to tell whether he's a man or a woman based
on his voice. Okay, so somebody that obviously is something that has
very much like not, you know, male maturity and aspects which are
sort of seen as more feminine is at least a piece of
it, not the only thing.
So that's, so that's that. Again, I'm not exactly sure what physical
condition this is paralleling. Charlie, you should have been, I should have
had you be on your Wikipedia and telling us what actual contemporary
condition this is paralleling.
Anyway, so the lack of pubic hair and then one of these
other...
Oh, well let's take a look. Is it all of these things
or one of these things? We'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara.
ואיזו היא אילונית, ve'eizu hi ailonit, what's an אילונית? ailonit? Which is
the female counterpart, and as we're seeing, it's really something about the
whole body and it's not just something about being infertile. ואיזו היא
אילונית, ve'eizu hi ailonit, כל שבת עשרים ולא הביאה שתי שערות, kol
shebat esrim velo hevia shetei se'arot, 20 without two pubic hairs, ואפילו
הביאה לאחר מכאן, ve'afilu hevia le'achar mikan, even if the pubic hairs
come after 20, הרי היא כאילונית לכל דבריה, harei hi ke'ailonit lechol
devareha, that does not lead to a reassessment, she remains an אילונית.
ailonit. ואלו הן סימניה, ve'eilu hen simaneha, these are her physical signs,
characteristics: כל שאין לה דדין, kol she'ein lah dadin, any woman that
doesn't have breasts, you know, that they haven't really developed, ומתקשה בשעת
תשמיש, umitkasheh besha'at tashmish, and sex is difficult for her. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר כל שאין לה שיפולי מעיים, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer kol she'ein lah shipulei me'ayim, she does not have the, what
is that called, the Mons Venus, the bump above the pubic area.
The Mons something else?
No women in this year. Nobody here, no doctors either. Anyway, there's
the, alright, there's that bump above the pubic area, that's what that's
referring to, so that she doesn't have that, it's
flat כנשים. kenashim. רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר כל שקולה עבה, Rabban
Shimon ben Elazar omer kol shekolah aveh, the opposite of what you
had by the man, a low voice, ואינה ניכרת בין אשה לאיש,
ve'eina nikeret bein isha le'ish, and again it's that you can't tell
whether it's a woman's voice or a man's voice. Yes?
There are men with high-pitched voices, totally
normal, and there are women with deep-pitched voices, totally normal, and if
you go to choral concerts you actually see men with women's voices.
Okay, so first of all, I'm not sure if this is singing
voice or talking voice, this is more talking voice, but secondly, it's
in, secondly, it's in combination with not having, being 20 and not
having pubic hair and maybe in combination of all of these together.
So let's take a look. Okay, so I'm just taking a look...
Okay, so
Mons pubis is the name, okay, of that שיפולי מעיים. shipulei me'ayim.
Okay, איתמר, itmar, so,
איתמר, itmar, סימני סריס, simanei saris, now how do you, now which
of these סימנים, simanim, like what do you do with the whole
list? So סימני סריס, simanei saris, רב הונא אמר עד שיהיו כולם,
Rav Huna amar ad sheyihyu kulam, only if somebody's a סריס saris
only if he has all of these סימנים. simanim. רבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו באחד מהן, Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu be'echad mehen, even one of
them puts a person in that category. היכא דהביא שתי שערות, heicha
deheivi shetei se'arot, now the גמרא Gemara clarifies, היכא דהביא שתי שערות
בזקן, heicha deheivi shetei se'arot bazeikan, when you have two hairs in,
two hairs of your beard. Now, the הגר"א Grah takes out the
word beard, so there's a whole question how to read this. If
we'll read it like the הגר"א, Grah, which is if you have
two pubic hairs,
then it's easier. I mean, we're not talking about facial hair, we're
talking about pubic hair. So if you have pubic hair, everybody agrees
to outweigh the presence of pubic hair, you need to have all
the סימנים. simanim. כי פליגי בשלא הביא, ki pligi beshelo heivi, when
you don't have pubic hair...
become bar mitzvah, have two pubic hairs,
and then have all these סימנים simanim and that would outweigh it.
Maybe these סימנים simanim had to be identified already at the time
of bar mitzvah, I don't know. But anyway, that's the way the
הגר"א Grah reads it, that all these סימנים simanim would outweigh pubic
hair. The other way is saying that it's not outweighing pubic hair,
no, pubic hair prevents a person from being a סריס saris straight
out, but it would over, but it's a question about if a
person has facial hair. Facial hair would be evidence that a person
isn't a סריס saris and that would need all of these things
to outweigh it. כי פליגי בשלא הביא, ki pligi beshelo heivi, the
case is that you don't have either pubic hair or facial hair.
And then do you need all these סימנים simanim or just one
of them? אלא הא דאמר להו רבא בר רב הונא לרבנן, ela
ha de'amar lehu Rava bar Rav Huna lerabanan, so that that Rava
bar Rav Huna said to the rabbis, עינו בי רב נחמן, inu
bei Rav Nachman, אי בשרו מעלה הבל, i besaro ma'aleh havel, so
this is fascinating. Apparently Rav Nachman, there was a question whether he
was a סריס. saris. So he said to the rabbis, go check
when you see Rav Nachman shower if steam comes off of his
body and then we'll know that he has one of the סימני
סריס simanei saris and that he's a סריס. saris. Okay, I don't
know who was checking to see whether Rav Nachman had pubic hair
or not. But anyway, so and if that does happen, then אסיב
ליה ברת, asiv lei brat, so then you can marry off your
daughter to him because you'll know that he isn't a סריס. saris.
So he was looking only for one סימן. siman. I don't know
for whatever reason he suspected that that was the case by Rav
Nachman. So how could it be he was looking for only one
סימן? siman? לדרב הונא, leRav Huna, it sounds like he's going with
Rav Huna that says one סימן siman is enough.
But the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no. רב נחמן סיכי דקנא
הוו ליה. Rav Nachman sichei dikna havu leh. No, Rav Nachman actually
had, again, either the word is he had like little stubble of
the beard, or he had little pubic hairs. Again, I don't know
who knows. But anyway, and therefore it was a case where everybody
agreed that he would need all the סימנים simanim to be a
סריס. saris. So as long as you saw one_ counter סימן, siman,
you knew he wouldn't be a סריס, sris, right? Because he said
if as long as you see one thing that's not a problem,
you're good. Okay? So why is it that he's פסקנינג paskening you
need all of them? No, he's not necessarily פסקנינג paskening you need
all of them, it could be a case where he had the
hair, and when you have hair, either pubic hair or facial hair,
then everybody agrees you need all the סימנים simanim to be a
סריס, sris, and if רב נחמן Rav Nachman didn't have even one
of the סימנים simanim didn't have, then we knew he was not
a סריס. sris. I still find it fascinating that the גמרא Gemara
thinks that that might have been the case by רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman. Let's just read the next two lines, get to the bottom
of the page. הסריס שחלץ ולא יבם וכן אילונית. HaSris shechalatz velo
yibem vechein ailonit. So we asked after the whole debate of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer what a סריס sris
whether you go by סריס חמה sris chama or סריס אדם, sris
adam, you have the סתם משנה stam mishnah at the end that
just said a סריס sris doesn't do חליצה chalitzah and didn't tell
you which type of סריס. sris. So the גמרא Gemara says,
קתני סריס דומיא דאילונית. katani sris dumya d'ailonit. So since the end
of the משנה mishnah mentioned סריס sris and אילונית, ailonit, presumably we're
talking about the same category. מה אילונית בידי שמים? Mah ailonit bidei
Shamayim? אילונית Ailonit is clearly not a category of physical injury. אילונית
Ailonit is a natural condition. אף סריס בידי שמים. Af sris bidei
Shamayim. So when it says a סריס sris doesn't do חליצה, chalitzah,
we're also talking about a natural condition סריס, sris, meaning a סריס
חמה. sris chama. וסתמא כרבי עקיבא. Vestama k'Rabbi Akiva.
And the סתם משנה stam mishnah at the end is ruling like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva when it excludes a סריס sris from חליצה
chalitzah and ייבום, yibbum, it's talking about a natural סריס, sris, like
an אילונית, ailonit, which is רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position. דאמר בידי
אדם אין. De'amar bidei adam in. Only a person who is a
סריס בידי אדם sris bidei adam does חליצה chalitzah and ייבום. yibbum.
בידי שמים לא. Bidei Shamayim lo. A natural occurring סריס sris does
not do חליצה chalitzah and ייבום, yibbum, and that is the simple
sense of the end of the משנה. mishnah. I guess we could
actually go even a little further, get to the next page. הסריס
שחלץ ליבמתו לא פסלה. HaSris shechalatz liyivamtou lo paslah.
If the סריס sris did חליצה chalitzah to his sister-in-law, he does
not invalidate her
because it's not a meaningful חליצה. chalitzah. If he does an act
of ייבום, yibbum, then it's an איסור עריות, issur arayot, it's his
sister-in-law, it's not במקום ייבום, bimkom yibbum, and he does make her
פסולה לכהונה. psulah l'kehunah. So the גמרא Gemara says, טעמא דבעלה הוא.
Ta'ama d'ba'alah hu. It sounds like because he had sex with her
and then it was an איסור כרת, issur kareth, that's why he
makes her a חללה. chalalah. הא אחר לא? Ha acher lo? If
another man had sex with her, she would not be a חללה.
chalalah. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב המנונא? Leima tihvei tiyuvta d'Rav Hamnuna? Maybe
this is a challenge to רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, דאמר שומרת יבם
שזינתה פסולה ליבמה, de'amar shomeret yavam shezintah psulah liyivamah, that a שומרת
יבם shomeret yavam who had sex with another
man, not with her brother-in-law, she is invalid because basically being a
שומרת יבם shomeret yavam is a quasi-marriage, right, זיקה, zikah, and therefore
sex with another man makes her sort of like an אשת איש,
eishet ish, not exactly, but would be enough to invalidate her. So
the גמרא Gemara says, so this woman, it's not just if this
brother who's a סריס sris has sex with her invalidates her, if
she has sex with any man that isn't a brother-in-law who has
a מצות ייבום. mitzvot yibbum. Now of course it could be that
this guy is the only brother, and then since he has no
מצות ייבום mitzvot yibbum the woman doesn't even need חליצה chalitzah or
ייבום. yibbum. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is assuming there are other
brothers, she's still a שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, so any man that
has sex with her makes her invalid to the other brother-in-laws, you
know, makes her like a case of a סוטה, sotah, and therefore
why is it only if this man had sex? So the גמרא
Gemara says,
לא, lo, הוא הדין אפילו לאחר נמי. hu hadin afilu l'acher nami.
No, it's right, even if somebody else had sex with her and
she was a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam she would be invalid. ואיידי
דתנא רישא בדידיה, Ve'aydi d'tana reisha bididei, but since initially we're talking
about this man, if he did חליצה chalitzah to her, right, and
we have to say that his חליצה chalitzah is not meaningful, so
תנא נמי סיפא בדידיה. tana nami seifa bididei. We said but if
he did ייבום yibbum with her it invalidates her. Okay, it's actually,
but it's true, if anybody did חליצה chalitzah with her when she's
a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. I don't know, I think it's even
more of a חידוש chiddush if he did חליצה, chalitzah, because him
you would think he's the brother-in-law, so maybe the חליצה chalitzah would
not invalidate. Let's just finish the משנה. mishnah. וכן אילונית שחלצו לה
אחים, Vechein ailonit shechalzu lah achim, or an אילונית, ailonit, right, who
the brothers did חליצה chalitzah does not invalidate her, and if the
brothers do ייבום yibbum it does invalidate her, because again, it's a
case of אשת אח, eishet ach, it's an איסור עריות issur arayot
without a מצות ייבום. mitzvot yibbum. So the גמרא Gemara says, טעמא
דבעלוה, Ta'ama d'ba'aluha, the reason they've invalidated, would invalidate her, is if
they had sex with her. הא לא בעלוה לא. Ha lo ba'aluha
lo. If not, they would not invalidate her. Just by the virtue
that she's by virtue of the fact that she's an אילונית ailonit
would not itself make her אסור assur to anybody else, to a
כהן kohen or anyone. So כמאן? Keman? Who is this going like?
דלא כרבי יהודה, D'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda, not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
דאי רבי יהודה אמר אילונית זונה היא. De'ei Rabbi Yehuda amar ailonit
zonah hi. Remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who said that an אילונית
ailonit is a woman who since she could never have children, every
act of sex is considered like fornication, that without the context of
procreation, it's considered fundamentally זנות. znut. So this משנה mishnah does not
assume that. It assumes that this אילונית ailonit is not a זונה,
zonah, can marry a כהן, kohen, and would only be a problem
if she had sex with the brother-in-law since it was not a
place of a מצוה. mitzvah. That would invalidate her, but otherwise she
would remain מותר mutar to a כהן. kohen. Okay, and we are
now totally caught up.